<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>France no friend to England. Or, The resentments of the French upon the success of the English. As it is expressed in a most humble and important remonstrance to the King of France, upon the surrendring of the maritime ports of Flanders into the hands of the English. Wherein, much of the private transactions between Cardinal Mazarin and the late Protector Oliver, are discovered. Translated out of French.</title>
            <title>Très humble et très importante remonstrance au roi, sur le remise des places maritimes de Flandres entre les mains des Anglois. English.</title>
            <author>Retz, Jean François Paul de Gondi de, 1613-1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91712</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1186</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E986_21</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203406</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863369</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863369</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168620</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91712)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168620)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 147:E986[21])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>France no friend to England. Or, The resentments of the French upon the success of the English. As it is expressed in a most humble and important remonstrance to the King of France, upon the surrendring of the maritime ports of Flanders into the hands of the English. Wherein, much of the private transactions between Cardinal Mazarin and the late Protector Oliver, are discovered. Translated out of French.</title>
                  <title>Très humble et très importante remonstrance au roi, sur le remise des places maritimes de Flandres entre les mains des Anglois. English.</title>
                  <author>Retz, Jean François Paul de Gondi de, 1613-1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 25, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year, 1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Retz, Jean François Paul de Gondi de. Très humble et très importante remonstrance au roi, sur le remise des places maritimes de Flandres entre les mains des Anglois.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 15".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658.</term>
               <term>Mazarin, Jules, 1602-1661.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  France --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  Foreign relations --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168620:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>FRANCE No Friend to ENGLAND. OR, The Reſentments of the FRENCH upon the Succeſs of the ENGLISH.</p>
            <p>As it is Expreſſed in a moſt Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Important REMONSTRANCE to the King of <hi>France,</hi> upon the Surrendring of the Maritime Ports of <hi>Flanders</hi> into the hands of the ENGLISH.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein,</hi> Much of the Private Tranſactions between CARDINAL <hi>MAZARIN</hi> and the late PROTECTOR <hi>OLIVER,</hi> are diſcovered.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of FRENCH.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:168620:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168620:2"/>
            <head>A Moſt Humble and Important REMONSTRANCE To The KING OF FRANCE. <hi>Upon the ſurrendring of the Maritime Ports of Flanders, into the hands of the Engliſh.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>VVE bring unto Your Majeſty the reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of all <hi>France,</hi> or rather thoſe of all the Catholick parts of Europe, which crieth for Juſtice upon the moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian of Kings, for one of the Inſupportableſt, and moſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168620:3"/>outragious injuries, that haply the Church ever yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſince its nativity upon earth. Is it poſſible that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Reign of <hi>Lewis</hi> the 14. the Altars ſhould be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrown upon the frontiers of <hi>France,</hi> which his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Predeceſſors, hath ſemented with their own proper blood in Paleſtine. Is it poſſible that the victorious Arms ſhould not be imployed but for to aboliſh and exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate the Sacraments, which ſanctifieth them? Is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that that Sacrifice ſhould be crowned, wherein the blood of <hi>Henry</hi> the Great is Immolated to the fury of a Parricide, by the inhumane baniſhment of the King of <hi>England,</hi> driven out of the Kingdome by his orders; nay, that the ſhameful Sacrifice ſhould be crowned by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanation of the blood of Jeſus Chriſt it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Pardon, great Sir, the importunity of the ſubject, which conſtrains us to open our mouths. Thoſe pathetick mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of a moſt bitter ſorrow, are only incouraged by the Intereſt of your ſacred Perſon, by the glory of your Crown, and by the zeal which we owe to Religion. That ſo dilicate tenderneſs, we have alwayes had towards all that, which carries the ſacred name of your Maj. can hardly juſtifie to poſterity, the reſpectful ſilence we have kept hitherto (contrary to all the Maximes, which in all times were received in <hi>France</hi>) upon the oppreſſion of your people, upon ſo much injuſtice done to the publick and the private, upon the infraction of all the ancient Laws of the Realm; and indeed Sir, our moderation would have chang'd into prevarication and impiety, if our tongues had not followed the motions of our heart, at the aſpect of ſo many eminent places, I mean thoſe abominable Idols, which hath almoſt obfuſcated the light of our Churches, ſince they raiſe them upon the ruines of temples, which threatneth us with the cruelleſt rebellion, that ever cruſhed a Crown, and the moſt deſperate Hereſie, that ever yet attempted the diſhonouring of the Church, and Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:168620:3"/>
            <p>We doubt not, Sir, but if the providence of God, let this work fall into your hands, they will imploy all the falſe colours (to render it black and odious to your Royal Judgment) wherewith, intereſted flattery ſerves it ſelf in the Courts of great Princes, for to diſguiſe the moſt important verities. They often condemn under the odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous titles of Libells and Pamphlets the moſt neceſſary Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrances, eſpecially at ſuch times, as they conſecrate under the ſpecious pretexts of your Princes ſervice, ſuch actions as are moſt diſadvantagious to his State and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and thoſe who formerly took the liberty to repreſent to their Kings of the firſt race, the extream prejudice which their Sovereign Authority received by the miſgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Stewards of their Pallaces, were moſt ſeverely puniſht as Rebells, nay, at ſuch times, as thoſe, who were upon the point of diſthroning them, were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenced as moſt faithful and obedient ſubjects. Sir, be pleaſed to judg of this piece, according to the nature of the matter its made of. If it be true, that it is a collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on only of detraction, and calumnies (as ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented to your Maj.) then ſuppreſs it with all the rigor, that Soveraign Authority oweth to the chaſtiſement of preſumptuous licentiouſneſs. But if on the contrary, it does only purely and ſimply diſcourſe of the miſtery of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, which they keep occult from the eyes of your Maj. and if it be not only true in all its parts, but alſo very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant to the good of your ſervice, and that of all your Realm, received as an inſpiration from heaven, which hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a regard of the purity of your intentions, ſetteth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you the precepts of your duty, by the groanings of your people, rather then by advertiſement, which God often ſendeth to ſuch Monarchs, as contemneth his Law: We doubt not, Sir, but that your Maj. ſtudies it with all the care poſſibly you can, and that in the frequent entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of piety, which are ſo uſual to your Maj you do not ſtrongly attach your ſelf to the Doctrine of the world, which teaches us, That one is not more obliged
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168620:4"/>to know what his Dutie is, then he is to do, ſo much as he knoweth of the ſame: This obligation is indiſpenſible and common to all the world; and certainly Princes ought to make greater reflection upon it then others, being more expoſed to the danger of being ſeduced by the fallacious Sophiſtry of Caſuiſts, and the artificious intrigues of their Miniſters then the common ſort of men are.</p>
            <p>All Chriſtendome, which admireth the greatneſs of your Virtues, hath not doubted but that in reſpect of what paſt betwixt the Councel of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Cromwell</hi> of late years, the good inclinations of your Majeſty were often forced by the pretended neceſſity of your State, and your fair twins of light often troubled at the Traiterous artifice of your Miniſters.</p>
            <p>Sir, one cannot believe that your Majeſtie hath been ever informed of the miſerable Eſtate of the Qu. of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> your Aunt, who is leaſt even in mendicity, only to pleaſe the cruel Aſſaſſinate of her Royal Spouſe. One could not imagin, Sir, that the blood of the great <hi>Henry,</hi> which gives you your being, could ſo unnaturally abandon his daughter and her little Infants even at the indigencie of bread, which never fails the moſt miſerable: who can ever perſwade himſelf that your royal Soul could ever have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the alienation, or rather proſcription of the King of <hi>England,</hi> your Cozen German and your Ally? Is it any thing elſe, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>, then the Phlebotomy of your own proper blood which a fortunate Politician draws, as if it were from your veins, to ſacrifice it to the Pannick terror of an Uſurper? How, Sir, what imagination can figure ſuch a thing as that the Monarch of <hi>France,</hi> Prince of the moſt warlike and moſt generous Nation in the Univerſe, could conſent to ſuch baſeneſs, as to make the nobleſt Crown of the world ſtoop to the moſt Capricious Idol that ever yet carryed favour with fortune.</p>
            <p>This falſe Protector of <hi>England</hi> takes a reſolution to Conſecrate his deteſtable Tyranny, by the preheminence he would have given his fantaſtical Government before
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168620:4"/>the Auguſt Crown of the Lil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies, and <hi>France</hi> fails not to obey his orders punctually. Her Pavillion which hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly triumphed over all the Nations of the world, which made the <hi>Saraſens</hi> tremble, which brought terror into all the Seas, which notwithſtanding the rude captivity of <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis</hi> the Firſt, had never abated their courage before all the forces of <hi>Spain,</hi> yet this ſo glorious a Pavillion humbleth it ſelf at the leaſt ſignal of a Pyrate, which commandeth the Barke of a Tyrant, the murderer of your Uncle.</p>
            <p>This Tyrant is not contented with all thoſe marks of honour, which from the firſt foundation of our Monarchy was not granted to any other but him only; he pretends to more ſolid ones, he uſurps and encroaches upon new <hi>France;</hi> and, as if he had not believed the advantages which he has upon your Crown to be eſtabliſhed enough by a conqueſt, which the weakneſs of your Miniſter ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſo eaſie to him, he ſtrives to hold the honour of your Predeceſſors; he detracts from their Glory, he abates their Trophies, by renouncing that ſo Illuſtrious a right of ſo glorious a mark of their ancient Victories, of this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable cuſtome which forc't the Engliſh to leave their Cannons as an eternal Monument of their defeat in the mouth of the River of <hi>Bourdeaux.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is, Sir, as if your Miniſter were of intelligence with him, to avenge the ſhame of the <hi>Bedfords</hi> and <hi>Talbots,</hi> he forceth you even by the advice of your Council to quit thoſe famous prerogatives, which frameth alwayes neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary reputation to great States, in thoſe Treaties where you gain Nothing, where you loſe Much, where you hazard All; where all things are ſealed up with the Auguſt name of a Brother, which you give to a Souldier who hath no other Throne but the Scaffold, upon which he Maſſacred the Kindred of <hi>Henry</hi> the Great.</p>
            <p>This conduct, Sir, cannot without difficulty find credit in after ages; ours does your Majeſty great injuſtice by its preſence; neither is there that man who doth not reſent with a great deal of regret, your Majeſty being ſerv'd by
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168620:5"/>ſuch blind and unfaithful Miniſters, and that you ſhould be led by the falſe opticks of a feeble and ignorant Polititian.</p>
            <p>There is no body condemns your Majeſty; and all the world knoweth, that thoſe temerities and abominations pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from a meer ſtranger, contrary in all points to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intentions of your Maj. being ſurprized by the ſame arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers that hath often deceived the moſt circumſpect Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that ever were; being ſurprized, I ſay, by the ſame means, that made <hi>Solomon</hi> the wiſeſt of Kings confeſs, that flattery and backbiting were the inevitable deſtruction of Princes; but adds immediately after, that God illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minates their hearts at the very inſtant of their ſtrongeſt temptations.</p>
            <p>Behold, Sir, this is the moment, at which we ought more then ever, implore heaven for that illumination of your heart, ſince the iniquity of your miniſter is come to its height, and ſince the ſurrendring of the Sea Ports of <hi>Flanders</hi> to the Engliſh, can furniſh with ſufficient mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the moſt dangerous and pernicious temptations, that are capable to make trial of the piety of a moſt Chriſtian King. We doubt not, Sir, but your Maj. hath ſhed tears of blood, when theſe precious pledges were given Hereſie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your name; neither do we doubt but that to force your inclinations to an action of that nature, they were fain to imploy all the Authority of the body politick, and of a more ſubtil cunningneſs, void of all ſorts of religion. You have aſſuredly ſhak'd and trembled both for the fear and anger, at the firſt propoſition of ſo fatal a blow given to the Holy Catholick faith; and when you have repreſented to your ſelf her Altar demoliſhed, her Temples prophaned, her miſteries violated, without doubt the blood of S. <hi>Lewis</hi> beſtirr'd it ſelf within your entrails at the ſight of ſuch ſpectacles, as would certainly have ſtrucken horrour into the heart of the moſt obſtinate Miſcreant. But they over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came all the difficulties, Sir, by thoſe reaſons by which they commonly give the reaſons of the State, and becauſe they might have ſome pretext, not to diſcover the frailties and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168620:5"/>ruinous foundation with which they propt them, they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg ſuch Maximes unto your Maj. as have no kind of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with that which paſſeth to day in the world; and I am ſure they have not failed to employ all the colours that can cover and diſguiſe an action of this nature. But God, Sir, obligeth your Majeſty to mingle them together, and weigh them in the ſcales of Reaſon, which can juſtly ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance this queſtion; and I ſhall endeavour to expound it to your Maj. with all the candor that the ſubject I treat of requireth of me; and I hope to make it clearly known to you that the Councel of your Miniſter upon this point, is and was both inſupportable and inſuſtentable by all divine and humane reaſons. The moſt licentious and abandoned The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologie, nay, that is moſt inſervient to the maximes of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiavel,</hi> can neither maintain nor juſtifie the ſurrendring of the Ports of <hi>Flanders</hi> into the hands of the Engliſh, but by the appearance only of a neceſſity of State, whereby they endeavour to ſhuffle up this ſhameful action, which is like to ſuppreſs utterly our holy Faith, even in one of the moſt Catholick Countries in the world, and the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found and artificialeſt Polititian that is, cannot defend a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution that doth ſo powerfully eſtabliſh on this ſide the Sea the moſt redoubtable and moſt ancient enemy of our Crown, unleſs it be by the falſe colours he might borrow from the imaginary health of your State. There is not that Caſuiſt ſo proſtitute in the world, no nor that Courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan upon the earth ſo far loſt, that can juſtifie this action by any other reaſons, then by ſuch as are drawn (at leaſt accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their diſcourſe) from the preſervation of your King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: and of this point, Sir, which can receive no difficulty, we conclude, That to judg wholſomly of the queſtion now in hand, we are only to conſider. Whether it is neceſſary or no? which we muſt ſound to the bottom, and let your Maj. know. That the compliance they have had upon this occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the Engliſh, was not only inutile to the good of your ſervice, but alſo moſt diſadvantageous to your Crown, and that in all the circumſtances that can condemn an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudent and blind Reſolution.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:168620:6"/>
            <p>We doubt not, Sir, but they repreſent unto your Maj. the great advantage you receive by thoſe ſuccours <hi>England</hi> ſende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h to your Army, and that to induce your Maj. to follow thoſe ſuggeſtions they would have inſpired into your heart upon this ſubject; they do alſo repreſent the Engliſh with their ſwords in their hands, ſtanding alſo up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the pretended patrimony of their fathers. They have alſo made your Maj. apprehend the great danger of the Protectors combining with the Spaniard, and they have certainly ſo inſinuated into your mind as to render this new a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iance very plauſibly unto you: And all that couldmake the rupture thereof ſeem offenſive to your State. But we are fident, Sir, that they have omitted more then half the conſiderations they ſhould have made upon this ſubject, and that they have acted after the manner of them who deceiveth the ſight by taking away one half of the day from the objects they would have ſhown; and that your Miniſter keeps from your knowledg the moſt ſolid, and the moſt important part of your intereſt.</p>
            <p>We cannot deny, but that your Maj. had a great deal of Reaſon to wiſh the falling out betwixt <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> but we maintain you had none at all to buy the Rupture at the price of a publick Scandal, which eclipſeth the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of your Reign by ſuch unparallell'd baſeneſs, which ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcureth the ſplendor of your Renown, by ſuch tyes as makes you loſe your ancient Allies, by ſuch unneceſſary conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcentions which makes the Protector of <hi>England</hi> Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of the Hugonots in <hi>France,</hi> by the unbridled licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſneſs which made them build more then forty Temples ſince the death of the late King your Father of Sacred Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory; and by the giving up of thoſe places which gives the entry in the neareſt places to your Capital City, to the ancienteſt and mortalleſt enemie of your State.</p>
            <p>Sir, If all the forces of the Empire and <hi>Spain</hi> were tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphing in the midſt of your Provinces, if our fields were covered with the multitude of their Legions; if all <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> had conſpired againſt the <hi>Lillies,</hi> we ſhould never
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168620:6"/>have look't for any ſuccor from <hi>England,</hi> and if we had, certainly we ſhould have ſhed tears of blood to be reduced to ſo great a ſtraight, as to ſeek for conſolation in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity of Rebels, who would never have granted us any, but to our deſtruction. And we do firmly believe, Sir, that we ſhall never be brought to ſuch Extremities, as might make our intereſts depend from the good will of ſuch peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as have principles ſo directly oppoſite to ours. The Divine Providence, which ſo diffuſively ſpreads its benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction upon the Piety and Valour of your Majeſty, hath ordained far more auſpiciouſly the events of your happy deſtinie, ſtill Victorious over the indiſcreet follies of your Miniſter, ſhall more and more mark your dayes with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Victories.</p>
            <p>But, Sir, Is this to anſwer thoſe bleſſings of heaven? Is this to be ſenſible of the glory of your Reign? Is this to know the advantages of your Victories, to end them with the loſs of your Conqueſts, with the ſurrendring of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dike,</hi> and thoſe other preambles to the Siege of <hi>Dunkirke,</hi> which they forced out of your hands even with terrible me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances? You exhauſt your Treaſures, you ranſome your Subjects, you expoſe all your Nobility, all your Army is endangered every day; they fight againſt the element, they combat with the Rigour of the ſeaſon, and all thoſe ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glings more then humane, hath no other motive, but the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendring of the Key of <hi>Flanders</hi> unto a Nation which in two hundred years could not comfort themſelves of the loſs of that of <hi>France,</hi> in being deprived of <hi>Callais.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, whoſoever would had ſeen that which is done to day upon the Frontire of <hi>France</hi> drawn in a Table, he would certainly have conſidered it as a Capricious fancie of a Painter, who would have taken pleaſure to play with his own imaginations; or rather of a deſcription of a Maſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rade, where thoſe who enter the Liſts do only make their Swords gliſter for the divertiſement of the beholders. If one would have ſhewn on the one part thoſe vaſt fields of <hi>Dunkirke</hi> covered with Battalions; and on the other
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168620:7"/>part that little Territory of <hi>Mardike</hi> covered only with fourteen or fifteen hundred men, which looketh upon the motions of the others with their hands hanging looſe by their ſides; ſhould not one have greater reaſon to believe that the later were Senators of old <hi>Rome,</hi> who would for their own pleaſure and recreation, cauſe an Army of Gladiators, and ſlaves to fight before them; than to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin that this great multitude were compoſed of free borne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who with all their hearts ſacrificeth their lives and fortunes for the conſervation and glory of this handful of people? We ſee the remnant of 4000 men flying up and down the banks or dunes of <hi>Flanders</hi> only for the ſervice of 2 or 3000. Goviats or Crackropes, which <hi>England</hi> ſent in this ſmall number. We ſee them daily continue thoſe ſad engines, and projects of this bloody ſpectacle wherewith they make account to feed the greedy eyes of <hi>Cromwell</hi> towards the beginning of the next Campain; we ſee that this falſe Prophet beholdeth from the top of the Tower of <hi>London</hi> all thoſe combats, where all the blood that is ſpilt whether Spaniſh or French, is drawn as if it were in a ſacrifice, which we our ſelves do offer to his illuſions. And which is more deplorable in theſe tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions, it ſeems we are not contented to ſubject this age wherein we live, to the will of this tyrant, but that we do alſo affect to enſlave our poſterity to the Engliſh ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude by ſurrendring thoſe places ſo famous and ſo conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable in the world.</p>
            <p>Thoſe places are ſo conſiderable, Sir, that <hi>France</hi> could not endure they ſhould remaine in the power of <hi>Spain,</hi> whoſe Naval forces are well known to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing dreadful to your Maj. and your Miniſter is pleaſed to deliver them unto <hi>England</hi> which is already Miſtreſs of all the Seas; and who doth only conſider them as the firſt ſtep or degree upon which they will hereafter mount up the baſtions of <hi>Callis;</hi> if the weakneſs of your Miniſter doth not prevent them by opening the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168620:7"/>gates by virtue of a treaty. But, Sir. We humbly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicate unto you, that you would be pleaſed not to receive this which we now offer unto your Maj. as any ſpight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful exaggeration carried on by the wings of malice: It being evident, that there is not ſo long a way between <hi>Dunkirk</hi> and <hi>Callis,</hi> as there is between <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Dunkirk.</hi> The Protector who makes the Pavillion of <hi>France</hi> humble it ſelf before him, (which neither the <hi>Henryes</hi> nor the <hi>Edwards</hi> could ever have done) cannot behold with a good eye thoſe places in the hands of the <hi>French,</hi> which the aforeſaid Kings of <hi>England</hi> had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed in your Kingdom, wherein he keepeth by his Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence a party which thoſe Kings had not.</p>
            <p>And without doubt, Sir, he exaſperates daily that Ulcer which knaweth inceſſantly our own entrails within us; and the intereſt he aſſumes in the ſyllieſt creature, that belongeth to thoſe of the reformed R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gion, proveth pregnantly, that <hi>Mardike</hi> and <hi>Dunki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k</hi> are not the bounds he puts to his deſigns: God grant. Sir, that when this Daemon of ambition is once eſtabliſhed in the main Continent by your Maj. own forces, which gives him more advantages againſt your ſelf then he could have hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, in thirty years of open War againſt your Crown, That after he hath made parties of his own within your Kingdome, through the connivance or at leaſt the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of your Miniſter, who doth even Idolatrize him; God grant, I ſay, Sir, that he doth not convert all his forces againſt <hi>France</hi> it ſelf, which is without contradiction the object, which is moſt natural and obvious to his deſires. God grant, Sir, that thoſe places which we buy for him to day at the price of our blood, of our goods of our Honour, and of our conſciences, be not in a ſhort time the Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zins and Arſenals, that ſhall furniſh out the ammunition deſtined to batter down ours. God grant that thoſe places be not the refuges of thoſe Veſſels, which may hereafter block up our Havens. God grant that the influence <hi>Dunkirk</hi> has, does not make it ſelf ſenſible, even unto our reſidences.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:168620:8"/>
            <p>Sir. The moſt infallible Maxime for to judg wholſomly of the actions of men, is to examin their intereſts, which commonly are the Rules they preſcribe to their actions, and the delicateſt Politician doth not abſolutely reject the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures which might be drawn from their paſſions, being often mingled together and running almoſt inſenſibly into thoſe powers, which gives motion to the moſt important affaires.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that are perſwaded, that, as he had not faln out with the Catholick King, but through rage and choller, which made him arreſt all his Ships, and commit ſuch inſupporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Robberies upon the coaſt of <hi>Spaine,</hi> are alſo of this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, which hath alſo great deal of likelihood, as well in reſpect of <hi>Cromwell,</hi> as other Politicks; it being very credible, that the Furies wherewith he is agitated, doth of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten occupy that place in his ſpirit, which was deſtiny'd to the pure lights of reaſon.</p>
            <p>Sir, After what manner ſoever we manage our Judgment upon this matter, it is impoſſible for to divide it between the Protectors intereſts and his paſſions; and at whatſoever time we conſider both the one and the other, we find them in a perfect harmony, to conſpire againſt our greatneſs: neither can we think the ſeeming union that is betwixt your Crown and <hi>England</hi> for the preſent, to be any thing elſe, but a Captious Truce, which the Intereſt of the Protector hath violently extorted from his inclinations, hoping to be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter able to follow them, after that the inveiglement of your Miniſter ſhall have done forging, the moſt dangerous armes that can be employed againſt your Crown and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>It is in this Kingdome, Sir, where beſides other States which have but indirect alliances with the Houſe of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that he ſeeth at every inſtant the <hi>Manes</hi> or Ghoſt of <hi>Henry</hi> the great threatnings the Parricide of his Son in Law; it is in this Kingdome that he beholdeth Reigning ſo gloriouſly that blood which is confounded and mixt by many ſtraight alliances with that which he had ſo barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168620:8"/>ſpilt upon the Scaffold of <hi>White-hall.</hi> It is in this Kingdome that he ſeeth already form'd in the noble minds of the French, thoſe lightnings and tempeſts with which they ſhall hereafter chaſtiſe his criminal head, after that the providence of God ſhall through the loſs of your Miniſter, purifie their generous inclinations, ſo naturally devoted to Monarchy; the furies which alwayes agitateth Parricides, impoiſoneth daily the ulcerated and cankerous ſoul of this Tyrant, by the fear of the indignation which he cannot eſcape but in appearance only, by the diffidence he hath in your promiſes, which he ſeeth to be forc't from your inclinations by the hatred of your blood which he hath ſo outragiouſly injured; he knoweth too well that a Miniſter, which is capable to put into his hands that, which he durſt not pretend unto with all the force of his arms, is a Miniſter, which nature doth not produce in all times, and in all ages. He cannot expect to find in an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration which might happen (God knows when) in your Councel, thoſe faculties he hath met with in a blind and ſtupid Miniſter, whoſe ignorance he improveth ſo well that he would willingly p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>event thoſe ordinary reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in <hi>France,</hi> which perhaps in time would oppoſe the moſt rigorous and moſt ſubtil ſpirits; he would make uſe of that imbecillity to conquer our Country, which ſerves him now to deceive it; and all theſe confiderations joyned together will undoubtedly repreſent themſelves to his mind, and reduce him peradventure to his own natural Genius, which induced him to make war upon us by the ſpace of four years, with inſuppor-table Pyracies, without ever daigning to denounce any againſt us, as if he were minded to adde that diſdain, (to which we daily expoſe our ſelves) to the other damages which we ſuſtain in the ruin of our commerce, that Genius which though obliged by ſo ſolemn a Treatie, yet hinders him not upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, fromtreating us rather like ſlaves then allies; that Genius which is ſo fortified by a particular intereſt, alwayes inſeperable from ſuch avaritions ſouls as his, nay,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168620:9"/>by thoſe rapines and outragious Extortions which he can commit every hour in the ſight of our Ports, which are ſo near his and without compariſon, more commodious, more conſiderable and more profitable to him then all the advantages he can derive from the far reſearch of the Fleet of <hi>Spain,</hi> which one may ſay to be as uncertain as their courſe is in the vaſt extenſion of the Ocean. Thoſe projects which came to nothing in the Indies, but to his own confuſion, doth certainly, turn his reſtleſs and ambitious imaginations to other parts nearer home, and which are more expoſed to his Tyranny. He feeds his ſoul with thoſe Soaring Ideas of the ancient <hi>Brittans,</hi> which ſeems not to him ſo impoſſible as their examples; and without doubt, when he conſiders that the firſt of his Conqueſts coſts him but ſo little pains he ſooths up his ambitious thoughts, which Ferries him over our Seas, and repreſents unto him one time <hi>Guienne</hi> revolt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under his Standarts. and another time he fancyeth <hi>Normandie</hi> reduced under his Laws.</p>
            <p>But we hope, Sir, that God Almighty will limit thoſe vaſt deſigns by ſome extraordinary effect of his mercy upon poor <hi>England,</hi> now Tyrannized and oppreſſed; and that by a mighty ſtroke of his Juſtice, he will no longer ſuffer this Tyrant to uſurp the Lawful Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of that Auguſt Prince who is Couſin German to your Maj. and who does ſo perfectly anſwer, by his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, the Proximity of blood that is betwixt your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties.</p>
            <p>In that caſe, Sir, what advantage ſhall <hi>France</hi> find in the neceſſity they have reduced the King of <hi>England</hi> to, in Allying himſelf ſo ſtraitly with the King of <hi>Spain?</hi> In that caſe, Sir, may not we with great deal of reaſon complain of the little forecaſt of your Miniſter, who by a very peculiar addreſs againſt your Intereſt, ſhould joyn the moſt redoubtable puiſſance of the Sea, with the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rableſt forces of the Land that is in the world? In that caſe, Sir, ſhould not we with great deal of judgment ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168620:9"/>from a Lawful King juſtly incenſed that power which makes us now tremble, being in the hands of an uſurper whom we ſo often oblige, and ſo obſervantly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect? In that caſe, Sir, the ſame policy which yields up <hi>Dunkirk</hi> to the Changeling power of a Tyrant, raiſed only by the uncertain motions of a blind and capricious for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, ſhall not refuſe <hi>Callais</hi> to the ſoveraign authority of a Lawful Monarch, when his auſpicious deſtiny ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolidate both his Throne and Glory. Should we not judge, Sir, that as the hand of God is not yet ſeen over the crimes of <hi>Cromwell,</hi> ſo do they weaken the weight of theſe conſiderations, and according, the ordinary max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ime of your principal Miniſter, who is not accuſed of too much providence, they give no other anſwer to this kind of reaſoning, but that we moſt conform our ſelves to the Times, and take new parties according to new Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures. But we muſt humbly beg of your Maj. to make a more ſerious reflection upon this State, that this ſtraite and inviolable Alliance hath put all <hi>Europe</hi> in; and we doubt not but without expecting any revolution in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> or alteration in <hi>Cromwels</hi> partie, you will eaſily find out the extreme prejudice which this deſperate peace hath done to your Intereſts.</p>
            <p>Can your Majeſtie perſwade it ſelf, that the States of the United Provinces hath not conceived an Extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Jealouſie at this near neighbour-hood of the Engliſh? Or can your Majeſty believe that this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick, the wiſeſt that is in the Univerſe, doth not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely repine at the ſurrendring of thoſe Sea-Ports of <hi>Flanders</hi> unto the only Nation of the world, which contend with them for the Empire of the Seas? Hath not your Maj. reaſon to apprehend, that thoſe faithful places which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged with ſo much fidelity, valour and wiſdom the obligations they have owed unto your Crown, are not now toucht to the very quick, by the participation w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> you make of the moſt conſiderable places of the low Countries, to ſuch people as have ſcarce yet ſheathed the Swords, which
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168620:10"/>but a little before they ſo injuriouſly drew againſt the Hollanders? Can your Maj. doubt but thoſe prudent and Sage Politicks are well inform'd, that the Imbargo of their Veſſels, the interruption of their Commerce ſo advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious both to <hi>France</hi> and their State, the falſe complaints of their Embaſſador and Vice Admiral were only practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes concerted betwixt your Miniſter and <hi>Cromwell,</hi> for to reduce thoſe brave defenders of their Liberties, to be ſlaves to the fantaſtical-Capricio of <hi>England?</hi> Can your Maj. doubt but thoſe intereſts, ſo viſible and ſenſible to the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> are not powerfully animated by the recognizance which they owe by ſo many ſolemn Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to the Houſe of <hi>Orange;</hi> and that this recognizance does alſo wait upon the famous Ghoſts of the <hi>Williams,</hi> of the <hi>Fredericks,</hi> and of the <hi>Maurices,</hi> who all conjure your Maj. by thoſe inviolable tyes they have had with your Crown, not to concur to the deſtruction of that Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Houſe, which honoured theirs with a Princeſs of as great Virtue as Birth?</p>
            <p>☞ Can your Maj be ignorant of the difference there is betwixt <hi>England</hi> a Republick, and <hi>England</hi> a Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy; that one may conſider Great Brittain under a King, as a very conſiderable Country in <hi>Europe;</hi> but that it might be lookt upon under a Senate, which aſſumed ſuch a form, as makes it ſelf Formidable to all the Earth? And that this Conſideration makes, That no Prince in Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome will joyn with your Intereſt, ſo long as you contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the Eſtabliſhment of a Republick, which from the very firſt inſtant of its birth, embraceth both the one and the other Hemiſphere, and, as it were, in a bravery defieth the Univerſe.</p>
            <p>We have reaſon to ſuſpect, that Admiral <hi>Opdam</hi> had not with ſo much violence moleſted the Coaſts of <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall,</hi> had not <hi>Holland</hi> been diſturb'd in her own Frontier Neighbour-hood by the Engliſh. We have ſubject to fear that the attempts under hand which <hi>Cromwell</hi> made upon the Zound, were the true and real motives that made the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168620:10"/>States and <hi>Denmarke</hi> joyn with <hi>Spain;</hi> we fear that your Maj. loſeth all your moſt faithful and affectionate Allies, who confederate themſelves openly by reaſon of your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters compliance and ſubmiſſion to their ſworn E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies and Hereticks, who are prefer'd before the moſt Ancient, the moſt Sacred, and the moſt Inviolable Allian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of you Crown. The Holy See is manifeſtly injured by thoſe actions, which make Hereſie triumph in the midſt of her Churches; we put our ſelves in the ſitteſt condition to receive the juſt marks of her Indignation upon a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſo criminal a Nature, as is able to pour thunder up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our heads; we provoke her every day more and more, by ſuch circumſtances as are indeed very worthy the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch of Franticks.</p>
            <p>We loſe all our reputation among the Catholick Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, we purchaſe none amongſt that of the Poteſtant, whoſe greateſt body abhors the Protectors ridiculous Illuſions; and all the fruit of our proſtitution is but to confound our ſelves with the Independents, that is to ſay, The ſworn ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of all Crowns and Religions.</p>
            <p>Caſt your eyes, great Prince, upon your true and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid Intereſt, and diſcern with that fair light heaven hath given your Majeſty, that which is your real ſervice from the imaginary Intereſt, or rather, the ill underſtood Policy of your favourite, who by a Monſtrous Prodigy, which po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity ſhall hardly believe of your Maj. hath of that Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pre-eminence (hitherto alwayes inviolable) Eſtabliſhed upon the Frontiers of your Kingdom a Modern <hi>Attila,</hi> the Paricide of Royaltie; who is ſo blind as to permit a formidable party to form it ſelf in the middle of your State? Who in the midſt of your Triumphs abandons that which wiſdom would not permit to foregoe, after the loſs of four Battels, and can give no colour to this perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious conduct, but the inconvenience of a War, whoſe bad ſucceſs could never be more dangerous then the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy he hath applyed; I mean, that curſed remedy, or rather that fatal poyſon with which he hath broke the <hi>Munſter</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:168620:11"/>peace ſo glorious, and ſo advantagious to your Maj. hath ſpread ſo prodigally upon that ardent fewel which conſumes all Europe, to the end he might eternize the conflagration thereof.</p>
            <p>Here it is, Sir, that we find our ſelves put on by the pure and holy motions of truth, which opens our mouths, ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates our tongues, and ſtirs up our hearts to diſcover to your Maj. the grand miſtery of iniquity; that miſtery which is drawn from the bottom of hell: this is the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery whereof the cruel Demon of War hath made <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> depofitary, and another man too Sir, which the reſpect we owe to our Maj. will hardly let us name; we would if we could poſſibly turn it off from the heads of ſome of thoſe that have the Honour to come neer the moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian of Kings; but alas! Sir, deſpair hath overcome the tenderneſs of our deſires, one may ſtill ſuffer with patience that hath ſome hopes left him, and there is no affliction ſo great but might be qualified, if one had ſome hopes, (though never ſo long to come) to ſee an end of them.</p>
            <p>But, Sir, there can be no ſuch hopes in our misfortune, Europe is now condemned to all eternity to endure Warre and miſery; the Sea-Ports of <hi>Flanders</hi> have conſumed the fatal negotiation of Munſter; and if it be juſt that the ſame hand that broke the peace ſhould perpetuate the War; how can <hi>Spain</hi> ever conſent to a treaty without Reſtitution of thoſe places which were wont to ſupply <hi>Bruxels,</hi> or how can <hi>Cromwell</hi> condeſcend to a Reſtitution, which might advance the general peace, the greateſt block in the way of his fortune: Who could ever have believed that after 27. years of open War, <hi>France</hi> could be ſo unhappy as to put the general peace into his hands, who of all men hath the trueſt intereſt to break it; we ſay the trueſt, Sir, to diſtinguiſh his from that of others, who certainly have but an imaginary one in the rupture of it, (but on whom to the great diſturbance of the Chriſtian world) ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination hath as much influence in this point as real truth.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:168620:11"/>
            <p>It is in this place that we find our ſelves obliged to name more particularly then we have hither to done my L<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Cardi. <hi>Mazarine,</hi> being conſtrained by our ſubject to diſcover to your Maj the true motions that had engaged him to an acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which one might very well call the ſepulture or quick burying of the general peace: Mr. the Cardinal <hi>Mazarin,</hi> who had not timely enough given him the nouriſhment, that is neceſſary for a polititian imagined in his infancy; that the chief quality of an able man was never to do any good, and to that this natural inelination of his own he adds ſome Lecture of <hi>Machiavel</hi> where he learned this doctrine, that tumult and confuſion are two things always favora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſuch authorities as do not ſubſiſt of themſelves; beſides all this he got ſome kind of habitude of Cardinal <hi>Richlieu,</hi> who was naturally of an unquiet ſpirit, and in all theſe different Schools, he acquired certain general Maxims of Policy, and having neither well expounded them, nor underſtood them according to their geniuine ſenſe, he dreſſes himſelf ſo diſorderly in an apparel that was never made for him, and in this confuſion frameth an extravagant Idea, which perſwades him that to be a great Miniſter he muſt mar all, never make peace, but turn the world upſide down; his Eſſayes would have out-gone the Maſter piece of another, ſince 'twas no leſs then the rupture of the great and glorious peace of Munſter, which cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly would have been more advantagious to your Maj. then 30. years of War crowned with continual Victories; but as Card. <hi>Mazarin</hi> carryed himſelf in this tranſaction, in a manner that was very little diſguiſed, and was very fair from all diſſimulation, he ſoon after perceived the indignation, and diſpleaſure of the people, who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed againſt him with a great deal of rage and fury, for the fault he committed in procuring a Treaty, whoſe good ſucceſs was not indeed in his power to obſtruct, had he not by a publick Declaration manifeſted his aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the ſame, and this taught him ſince, that as an able Merchant will not forget any
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:168620:12"/>meaſure neceſſary for the weighing of his ware; ſo does not he omit any thing to further his deſigns of War, and ſuppreſs thoſe that might make for peace. Your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter runs with ſo much precipitation to diſturb the publick tranquillity, that his promptitude being joyned with his natural incapacity, doth not permit him to conſider what the event might be: He remembers the late Card. <hi>Richlieu</hi> had oppoſed the Armes of <hi>Guſtavus Adolphus,</hi> by which puiſſant diverſion the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> being loaded with the ſpoils of the Proteſtant and puſt up with <hi>Till ye</hi>'s Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories, threatned the deſigns of the late King your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Cardinal <hi>Mazarine</hi> who never applies general ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples to particular conjunctures, derives his ſuccour from the North, at ſuch times as <hi>Germany</hi> ſcarce yet breathing under the burthen of her miſeries and ſufferings; and forceth this dread<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and warlike Nation to put on their Harneſs, which is to be feared they'l not put off again ſo ſoon as could be wiſhed for your ſervices good.</p>
            <p>What ſhall become of this grand State trick, Sir? the Reunion of the King of <hi>Hungary, Poland, Denmark,</hi> the Elector of Saxony, and <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> and the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> together with the perpetual continuation of the Emperour in the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> which one King of <hi>Swedeland</hi> puiſſantly arm'd upon their frontiers, would have ballanc'd for a long time, and the uniform conſent of the Germans (as it was to be ſuppos'd) at the combuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they would have made in their Country; Charity teacheth us not to aſcr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>be all this to the ill intentions of Cardinal <hi>Mazarine,</hi> but leave ſomething to be imputed to the little light he hath to diſcern the times.</p>
            <p>But we cannot, unleſs we grant that if he had not fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen the unhappy events of his own enterprizes, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts himſelf when he conſiders it hath given ſome advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> which doth nothing pleaſe him, yet hath it in reſpect of the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neral peace produced main obſtructions which are infimtely pleaſing to him; we have the ſame thoughts of his conduct in <hi>Italy</hi> where
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:168620:12"/>we plainly ſee he hath animated <hi>Monſr de Modena,</hi> which diſcontents by ſuch unconſcionable practiſes, as do now exhauſt the pureſt blood and ſilver in <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſhall become of thoſe ſamous projects, the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of thoſe places where they raiſe as many ſieges, as they lay before others; the averſion of all neighbouring Princes eſtranged from us by the jealouſie they have of ſo unequal a treaty made with the Duke of <hi>Modena,</hi> and exaſperated by <hi>Monſr. de Mantua</hi> now ſiding with your enemies: The loſs of <hi>Gazal</hi> which brings ſo much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to <hi>Spain,</hi> as they durſt never pretend unto, if your Miniſter had not withall poſſible care, indeavoured to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t the affairs of your Maj. (by a continual confuſion) in ſuch a condition as is odious to all <hi>Italy;</hi> the acquiſition of <hi>Montfenr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t</hi> to the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> which formerly raiſed all Chriſtendom againſt it, is notwithſtanding now received as a moſtipleaſing news to all Princes.</p>
            <p>We believe that <hi>Monſr.</hi> the Cardinal had not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther foreſeen the fair effects of his own pollicy; but we are perſwaded the extream ſorrow he conceived at the ill ſucceſs of one of his deſigns, to wit, <hi>Monſr. de Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dona</hi>'s triumph, is much mitigated by the ſatisfaction he finds in thoſe obſtacles which his confuſions, (though not anſwering the expectation of his project) hath occaſioned to the General peace. And that which lets us ſee we are not deceived in this point, is, that as ſoon as he perceived thoſe ill ſucceſſes which fruſtrated his hope, diminiſh in ſome ſort, the ſtrength of thoſe obſtacle; which his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice imployed againſt there-union of the two Crowns; he embraces with unſpeakable eagerneſs his fatal meanes of their diſunion, forlever he precipitates with ſuch impetuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity to the ſurrendring the Maritime Ports of <hi>Flanders,</hi> that is to ſay, an action ſo manifeſtly prejudicial to your Maj. ſervice, that one can never ſuſpect his ignorance to have any ſhare in this Treachery, but that we muſt impute it intirely to his malice, which would have given this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal wound to the common prace of Chriſtendome.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:168620:13"/>
            <p>One cannot, Sir, impute this ſhameful reſolution to any other cauſe but to his inveterate malice, which made us fight under the Banners of the Protector of <hi>England,</hi> and which hath now forced us to end that field which had coſt us ſuch immenſe ſums of money, only to make a chain that might enſlave us to this Tyrant.</p>
            <p>It is now, Sir, more then 27 years, that I do not know what ſlight, and almoſt frivilous intereſt, had made all the earth ſhake and tremble by ſuch an impetuous moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as (if we had believed your Miniſter) all the men of the world could not reſiſt; and yet in the very firſt year of your unhappy Alliance with <hi>England,</hi> they deliver to <hi>Cromwell</hi> (more likely as a Homage, then by vertue of a Treaty) a Country far more conſiderable then all the places that had been the occaſion of the breach between the two Crowns. Thus we buy an Everlaſting War at a price at which one might have been aſhamed to purchaſe the moſt neceſſary peace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>France</hi> had formerly (even by the acknowledgment of your miniſter) preferred the continuation of the miſeries of all <hi>Europe,</hi> before it would have left the fortifications of <hi>Nancy</hi> in the hands of the Duke of <hi>Lorrain;</hi> nay, we have proffered to run the hazard of all immaginable revolutions (which are too contingent to great enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes) rather then leave one good place to a Petty Prince, even worn out by the proceſs of his own misfortunes. And we do now a dayes abandon ſuch Ports as are, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out contradiction, more important to a Commonwealth, which is far more redoubtable then the Duke of <hi>Lorraine;</hi> yet, with this difference, that in the reſtitution of <hi>Nan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> we might have found peace with <hi>Spain;</hi> and in the ſurrendring of <hi>Dunkirk</hi> we have found War with all <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What diſorder, Sir, or what confuſion hath not your Miniſter brought to all the Nations of the world, by this fatal action? the hopes of Conſolation, which alwayes accompanies and qualifies the greateſt misfortunes, is now
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:168620:13"/>taken away from us. His cruelty in revenging the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation the <hi>French</hi> have of his government, and conduct of your Perſon, is not ſatisfied with a misfortune, which, together with other Nations, is common to them; but he endeavours to ſtifle in us, as much as he can, the liberty of deſiring, which diſpair it ſelf could never utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly extinguiſh in us. He diſturbs the moſt ſacred and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable of our holy Vows, and by a monſtrous Prodig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, which Nature yet could never parallel, we find our ſelves (even at this inſtant) in an incapacity of diſcharging the moſt eſſential of all our obligations.</p>
            <p>In how ſad a condition, Sir, doth a French Catholick find himſelf in the Churches? and at the foot of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars muſt he implore the bleſſings of God upon the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of <hi>Spain,</hi> declared enemies of your Majeſty; or muſt he ſeek the favours of heaven upon thoſe of <hi>France,</hi> which a horrid and terrible blindneſs imployes for the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhing of Hereſie. Which ſhall we behold more willingly, the Croſs of <hi>Burgundy</hi> diſplayed on the top of our Baſtions, or that of <hi>England</hi> (which doth ſo crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally degenerate from it ſelf) triumphing upon Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Rampiers? Which ſhall we fooner deſire, Sir, the loſs of our own Colours conſecrated to Almighty God in the Churches of <hi>Bruxells,</hi> or the Standarts of Caſtile, dedicated to Divils in the Temples of <hi>London?</hi> What ſhall we wiſh for the ruine of your Armies animated by our own proper blood, before the Towns of <hi>Flanders,</hi> or the conqueſt of thoſe places which is, without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon, more prejudicial then their conſervation? We feel in our ſelves, Sir, we feel in our hearts a Combate of Religion againſt the State, and of the State againſt it ſelf: Shall we run next Summer to the Siege of <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> then to that of <hi>Oſtend,</hi> ſo to <hi>Newport,</hi> and all this to follow our Natural inclinations to obey our Prince? Or ſhall we ſtay at home, and implore the protection of God upon thoſe places, which ſerve as much, at leaſt, in the hands of the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> that they give the weakneſs of your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:168620:14"/>ſome means to ſatisfie <hi>Cromwells</hi> ambition for a year; by ſome other way then the giving up of <hi>Call is</hi> and <hi>Bullin?</hi> ſhall we in the Winter prepare branches of <hi>Lawrell</hi> to Crown the ſacred head of our Prince the next ſpring or ſhall we draw into a ſolittude, to bewail a misfortune that makes them wither as ſoon as they are gathered?</p>
            <p>In how doleful Eſtate, Sir, and in how deplorable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition doth poor <hi>France</hi> find it ſelf? at this very inſtant it ſeems ſhe doth delight to ſpoil her ſelf of all thoſe glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous advantages, ſhe had obtained over <hi>England</hi> in Ages paſt? it doth not ſuffice her now to efface the luſtre of her ancient Victories by this ſervile and dependant War, which ſhe make<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> under thoſe Standarts, which ſhe hath formerly with ſo much glory rent to pieces, but ſhe muſt yet for the ſatisfaction of <hi>Cromwell,</hi> renounce the reputation ſhe had acquired in the negotiations, and Treaties, they reckon, Sir, 600. years between the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> and that of <hi>England,</hi> ſince the unfortunate marriageof <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenor</hi> of <hi>Guienne</hi> and thoſe who make up this number, mark very judiciouſly that the Engliſh who were never-yet weary of conteſting the glory of Arms with our Nation, were forc'd to yerld to them at leaſt in points of Wiſdome and Policy.</p>
            <p>But alas! Sir, this advantagious opinion which we could never cheriſh with two much care in the hearts of all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, is now Raviſhed and buried in this laſt fatal Treaty of <hi>London,</hi> now we make <hi>England</hi> amends for all the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row we caus'd her in former times, in defending our ſelves ſo wiſely from all her ſubtleties, &amp; ſurprizes; the ſole nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation of Cardinal <hi>Mazarin</hi> ſhall ſufficiently revenge her to poſterity of all thoſe advantages we have gain'd upon her in more then 600 Treaties, and <hi>Cromwell</hi>'s fierceneſs, Victorious over the imbecillity of your Miniſter ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after quite extinguiſh the glory of our ancient politicians: Open your eyes then Great King upon this fatal blindneſs, upon this horrible illuſion, which rather obſcures then ſtops thoſe glorious exploits, which all Chriſtendome exnects from your Royal Virtues.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:168620:14"/>
            <p>Open your eyes, great Prince, upon the loſs of your Allies, which they drive ever with violence out of your intereſts, by the deſpair they are daily driven to by the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions they have that your Miniſter will never put an end to the miſeries of <hi>Europe.</hi> Open your eyes, great Prince, upon this mortal wound they have given to the general peace, which is the only object of the groans and tears of your people, which is aſſuredly the final end of your deſires, and ſhall be the work of your Piety and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, if God be Exorable to the Prayers and wiſhes of all your moſt Faithful Subjects.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
